"...Tim created a project called, Destination iPad, combining the iPad technology, Keynote presentation, and persuasive writing. It was such a new and innovative way to get persuasive writing to interest the students..."

K. Zienlinski Teacher, Charles F. Patton Middle School

"...I observed Tim's innovative teaching style which holds the individual responsible for his or her own learning as well as cooperative learning activities which challenge each student to communicate effectively, to cooperate with others, and to think critically..."

C. Sapyta Teacher,Charles F. Patton Middle School

"...Mr. Murphy has developed a positive bond with his students and they thoroughly enjoy his classes. He is very dedicated to his students and to delivering the curriculum in a creative and thorough manner ..."

K. Convery Teacher, Charles F. Patton Middle School

Timothy R. Murphy

1330 Crest Drive ■ West Chester, Pa 19382 ■ 610.246.6634 (cell) ■ coachmurph82@gmail.com.com

CERTIFIED SECONDARY ED. TEACHER (7-12)

Dedicated middle levels/secondary education teacher eager to resume full-time teaching career. Experienced instructor, coach, and lifelong learner with a passion for education and a commitment to optimizing student and school success.

Core Competencies

- Classroom Management
- Creative Lesson Planning
- Curriculum Development
- Differentiated Instruction
- Student Individualism
- Learner Assessment
- Technology Use in the Classroom
- Special Needs Students/IEPs

Experience

UNIONVILLE-CHADDS FORD SCHOOL DISTRICT - Kennett Square, PA

Charles F. Patton Middle School, Long Term Substitute – 2007 to present UHS Varsity Football Assistant Coach – wide receivers & defensive backs – 2008 to present CFPMS 7th Grade Boys Basketball Coach – 2007 to present CFPMS Track & Field Coach – 2008 to 2012 CFPMS Baseball Coach – 2013-present

Hired as a long-term substitute instructing middle level academic subject areas to both group and individual students in the Charles F. Patton Middle School, including various assignments beginning in the Fall of 2007 to the present. Subject areas taught at length are as follows:

2012-2013 - 1 section of 7^{th} grade Literacy, 1 section of 7^{th} grade At Literacy, 1 section of 8^{th} grade Core English, 2 sections of 7^{th} grade Extended Core English, helped write new 7^{th} grade Non-fiction Writing course.

2011-2012 – 2 sections of 6th grade Performing Arts, 3 sections of 7th grade English, remedial PSSA prep course, helped write new 7th grade Core and Extended Core English curriculum.

2010 - 2011 - Various Classes, (STS - per diem)

2009-2010 – 3 sections of 7th grade Literacy, 2 sections of 7th grade Social Studies. **Spring 2009** – 3 sections of 6th grade Literacy, 1 course of 6th grade first level

Mathematics, 1 course of 6th grade second level Mathematics.

2008 - 2009 - Various Classes, (STS - per diem)

2007-2008 – 8th grade Fundamental Pre-Algebra, 7th grade Foundations of Algebra Responsible for Study Island tutoring and PSSA review for 6th, 7th and 8th grade. Helped students that struggled with Study Island over a six-week period in order to prepare them for the PSSA Math test.

Key Contributions:

- Earned a reputation for the quality of classroom teaching, lesson plans and instructional materials used in teaching diverse subjects.
- Assisted in developing innovative approaches that were held as the model standard for meeting classroom and individual student goals in areas including mathematics, experiential learning, literacy and differentiated instruction.
- Worked as part of a team to create the new 7th grade Core and Extended Core English Curriculum.
- Consistently commended for ability to redirect students exhibiting behavior problems by replacing disruptive, unproductive patterns with positive behaviors.
- Participated in extra-curricular activities, coaching a high school varsity sport, and two middle school sports.

STUDENT TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Baldwin-Whitehall School District – Baldwin High School, Pittsburgh, PA

10th-12th grade Psychology of Personality, 10th-12th grade Psychology Participated as student council supervisor, tasks included executive board and regular committee meetings, as well as a student leadership conference at Gateway High School.

Education & Credentials

CERTIFICATIONS: Secondary Citizenship (7-12), Middle Levels Mathematics, Middle Levels Language Arts, and Anticipated Middle Levels Science

DUQUESNE UNIVERSITY — Pittsburgh, PA

BS in Secondary Education, 2007 – (QPA 3.47)

Pennsylvania Instructional I Certification (7-12)

Honors: Vice President – Kappa Delta Epsilon (honorary professional education fraternity)